欢迎收看《造物小百科》
On how it's made.
钢铁，从摩天大楼到桥梁
Steel, from skyscrapers to bridges,
它都是当之无愧的工业脊梁
it can be trusted to be the backbone of industry.
但这种可靠的建材是如何生产的呢？
But just how is this reliable building block produced?
苹果汁
Apple juice.
你以为苹果汁是在苹果离开果园后，才开始手工制作的吗？
Thought your apple juice was produced lovingly by hand after the apples leave the orchard?
那你就想错了
Well, think again.
起落架
Landing gear.
当承载超过35吨的飞机着陆时，这件关键设备必须能承受巨大的压力
When landing over 35,000 kilos of aeroplane, this critical piece of kit must be able to undergo fantastic stresses.
还有化妆品
And cosmetics.
香水、眼影和口红
Perfume, eye shadow, and lipstick,
有些产品含有50多种成分
with over 50 ingredients going into some products,
这个行业必须以最高标准运作
this industry needs to work to the highest of standards.
从摩天大楼到桥梁
But first, from skyscrapers to bridges,
从家用电器到汽车，以及其间的一切，都得益于它的强大
from household appliances to cars and everything in between, thanks to its legendary strength.
钢铁可以担当起工业的脊梁
steel can be trusted to be the backbone of industry.
但如何将地球上最丰富的资源转变为可靠的建材呢？
But how do you turn one of Earth's most abundant resources into a reliable building block?
钢铁由铁矿石或废钢制成
Steel is made from either iron ore or scrap metal.
在这家工厂里，利用的是废钢
In this operation, it's scrap that will be recycled.
用一台10吨的电磁铁，把压扁的车身
Using a 10-ton electromagnet, crushed car bodies,
家用电器、罐子等钢制废料都收集起来
electrical appliances, cans, and other steel scraps are gathered up.
这块强力磁铁能吊起5吨金属
This powerful magnet is able to lift 5 tons of metal.
其中约80%的废钢将被加工成钢条
About 80 percent of this scrap will be transformed into bars of steel.
这些金属随后被倒入料篮
This metal is then dumped into a basket,
料篮本身重达32吨
which alone weighs 32 tons.
料篮最多可装下惊人的60吨金属，它们将被熔炼成钢水
The basket can hold up to a staggering 60 tons of metal, which is going to be turned into molten metal.
熔炉温度可达1650摄氏度
This furnace reaches a temperature of 1,650 degrees centigrade,
足以熔化几乎所有物质
hot enough to liquefy just about anything.
熔炉由3根电极和4个天然气燃烧器加热
The furnace is heated by 3 electrodes and by 4 natural gas burners.
料篮中的金属被倒入熔炉
The contents of the basket are dumped into the furnace.
废料与熔化的钢水接触
The pieces of metal come into contact with liquefied steel.
排烟系统抽走产生的烟雾
And an aeration system draws out the smoke that's produced.
在如此高温下，60吨金属约需60分钟即可熔化
At this intense heat, the 60 tons of metal will melt in around 60 minutes.
金属熔化时，混合物中的杂质会浮到表面
This molten mix is composed of impurities which rise to the surface when the metal becomes liquefied.
此时，工人会取钢水样本以确定其化学成分
At this stage, a workman draws a sample of steel to determine its chemical makeup.
接着，喷枪向钢水吹入氧气
Next, a lance blows oxygen into the molten steel,
以降低其含碳量
which reduces its carbon content,
使混合液均匀并加快进程
homogenizing the mix and speeding up the process.
钢包被放置在熔炉下方
A ladle is positioned beneath the furnace.
钢水将从熔炉注入钢包
The molten steel will be transferred from the furnace into this ladle.
钢水轻松流入钢包
The molten steel easily pours into the ladle.
钢包重55吨，可容纳115吨钢水
The ladle weighs 55 tons and holds 115 tons of molten steel,
一台可吊起180吨的桥式起重机将它吊起
and an overhead crane capable of lifting 180 tons hoists its cargo.
为获得合适的钢质，会加入添加剂
Additives are introduced in order to obtain the correct steel tone.
电极从熔炉钢包中取出
Here, the electrodes are taken out of the furnace ladle.
工人现在打开分配器的浇注口
A workman now opens the pouring nozzles of the distributor.
钢水流入模具
The molten steel runs into molds.
钢水迅速冷却并开始凝固
It quickly cools and begins to harden.
钢坯长度在4.5米到10.6米之间
Steel billets are produced in lengths varying between 4.5 and 10.6 meters.
随后天然气割炬将钢坯切割成所需长度
The billets are then cut into the desired length with a natural gas torch.
用蜡笔在钢坯上标上浇铸识别号
A pouring identification number is marked on them with a wax crayon.
接下来还要对钢坯进行轧制
The flattening of the billets remains to be done.
全面轧制开始
The full flattening begins.
钢坯被送入熔炉，在1095摄氏度的温度下重新加热2小时
Billets are placed in the furnace to be reheated for 2 hours at 1,095 degrees centigrade.
水流冷却钢坯顶出装置
Water jets cool the billet ejector.
钢坯被放在轧机上
The billets are placed on the flattener,
强大的轧辊对其进行压缩
where powerful rollers compress them.
这一工序使钢坯达到所需的形状和尺寸
This operation gives the billets the required shape and size.
水冷轧辊碾轧钢坯
Water-cooled rollers crush the billets.
部分钢坯从12厘米的厚度压到14毫米
Some billets go from a thickness of 12 centimeters down to 14 millimeters
其余的则从15厘米压到19毫米
while others reduce from 15 centimeters down to 19 millimeters.
在生产的末端，钢条以高达35公里/时的速度前进
At the end of the production, bars move along at a speed reaching 35 kilometers per hour.
钢条达到所需尺寸后，必须进行冷却
Once they've reached their required dimensions, the bars must be cooled.
冷床能让钢条均匀冷却
This cooling bed allows the steel bars to cool uniformly.
这家工厂每年生产约40万吨钢条
A total of some 400,000 tons of steel bars are made at this plant each year.
你以为苹果汁是在苹果离开果园后才开始手工制作的吗？
Thought your apple juice was produced lovingly by hand after the apples leave the orchard?
那你就想错了
Well, think again.
和所有现代食品生产一样
Like all modern food production,
苹果汁也是工业化生产的
apple juice is made on an industrial scale,
而且必须如此
and it needs to be
因为仅一家工厂每年就要将4万吨苹果加工成果汁
as just one factory transforms 40,000 tons of apples into juice every year.
在加拿大魁北克，主要用麦金托什苹果来制作苹果汁
In Quebec, Canada, they make apple juice mainly from McIntosh apples.
麦金托什：加拿大的苹果品种, 苹果电脑的苹果就是这个品种
90%的果汁生产在10月的收获季完成
90 percent of juice production is done at harvest time in October.
工艺流程从传送带将苹果运往检验区开始
The process starts when a conveyor transports apples to an inspection location.
苹果逆着传送带的方向翻滚
Apples tumble in the reverse direction of the conveyor belt,
这样湿叶等杂物就会粘在传送带上
so that the wet leaves and other materials adhere to the belt.
苹果会在储罐中存放数小时
The apples are stored in silos for several hours.
为避免苹果在降落过程中被磕伤，阶梯式滑道会减缓它们下落
In order that the apples are not too bruised in their descent, they're slowed down in this stepped chute.
现在可以开始榨汁了
The juice making can now begin.
苹果先被清洗
The apples are washed.
第一道水浴洗去碎石
This first water bath eliminates pebbles,
因为这里既用采摘的苹果，也用地上的落果
as windfall apples are used as well as picked.
落果：从树上掉落而非采摘的苹果
一道冷水喷淋完成整个清洗过程
A shower of cool water completes the washing process.
苹果在这台粉碎机中被切成小块
The apples are cut into little pieces in this grinder.
为制成果浆，会加入酶来分解苹果的细胞结构
To produce gratings, enzymes are added which break down the cellular structure of the fruit
从而最大限度地榨取果汁
allowing for maximum juice extraction.
接着，果浆被送入浸渍罐
Next, the gratings are transferred into maceration reservoirs,
在里面静置60到90分钟
where they'll stay for 60 to 90 minutes.
随后开始榨汁
Then the juice is extracted.
果浆被泵入大功率液压机
The gratings are pumped into a powerful hydraulic press.
在压机内部，过滤袋挡住苹果皮、籽和茎
Inside the press, filter sleeves hold back the skins, seeds, and stems of the apples.
质量控制必须严格
Quality control has to be strict.
在每一道工序都会抽取果汁样本
At each stage of the process
确保卫生规范得到严格遵守
samples of juice are drawn off to make sure that the hygiene controls are well adhered to.
果汁经过过滤，最微小的颗粒也会被滤除
The juice is filtered so that the smallest of particles are held back.
果汁通过这些巨大的储罐逐级流动
Juice flows from one stage to the other via these immense reservoirs.
下一步是巴氏杀菌
The next step is pasteurisation.
果汁进入换热器，被加热到88摄氏度
Juice enters the exchanger and is heated up to 88 degrees centigrade,
然后再冷却回50摄氏度
then cooled back down to 50 degrees.
加入酶使果胶水化
Enzymes are added to hydrate the pectin.
这就是超滤过程，带有微孔的滤膜会截留最微小的颗粒
This is the ultrafiltration process, where filter membranes with microscopic pores retain the smallest of particles.
苹果汁现在已被完美过滤
The apple juice is now perfectly filtered.
其澄清度、风味、色泽和天然果糖含量都要经过检验
Its clarity is verified as well as its flavour, colour and natural fructose content.
由于果汁在10月生产
Since juice is produced in October,
必须保存起来供全年使用
it has to be conserved throughout the year.
一部分产品存放在无菌仓库中，等待全年陆续灌装
A portion of the production is stored in this sterile warehouse to await being bottled during the year.
每个储罐可容纳11万升过滤后的果汁
Each reservoir can hold 110,000 litres of filtered juice.
不添加任何防腐剂
No preserving agent is added.
接下来，果汁被倒入容器中
Next, the juice is poured into containers,
以每分钟100个的速度灌装
which are filled at a rate of 100 a minute.
随后容器被密封
The containers are then hermetically sealed.
喷上两道热熔胶来固定侧面的吸管
Two little sprays of hot glue are applied. This secures the straws attached to their sides.
另一条自动化生产线负责瓶装果汁
Another automated production line bottles the juice.
瓶子在传送带上排成一列循环移动
They circulate in a row on this conveyor.
在无菌室里，瓶子用双氧水清洗消毒
Bottles are washed and disinfected with hydrogen peroxide in this sterile room.
随后用无菌水冲洗，再送往灌装工位
Then they're rinsed with sterile water before being carried to the filling location.
每分钟有120瓶灌入巴氏杀菌后的苹果汁并封盖
Each minute, 120 bottles are filled with pasteurised apple juice and sealed with a cap.
瓶子随后贴上标签，发往发货区
Bottles are then labelled and sent to shipping.
这家工厂每年将2万到4万吨苹果加工成果汁
This plant transforms between 20,000 and 40,000 tons of apples into juice every year.
《造物小百科》稍后播出
Coming up in How It's Made
飞机起落架
Aircraft landing gear.
这件关键设备必须能承受巨大的压力
This critical piece of kit must be able to undergo fantastic stresses.
还有化妆品，有些产品含有50多种成分
And cosmetics, with over 50 ingredients going into some products,
这个行业必须以最高标准运作
this industry needs to work to the highest of standards.
广告之后见
See you after the break.
欢迎回到《造物小百科》
Welcome back to How It's Made.
稍后我们将探访化妆品行业
Later we look at the cosmetics industry.
这个行业必须以最高标准运作
This industry needs to work to the highest of standards.
升上去的终归要落下来
But first, what goes up must come down.
飞机的起落架必须能承受巨大的压力
The undercarriage of a plane must be able to undergo fantastic stresses.
这一关键的飞机部件是机械加工与尖端技术结合的产物
This critical piece of aircraft equipment is the product of expert mechanics combined with sophisticated technology.
这块沉重的钢材是KC-135R同温层加油机的起落架
This heavy piece of steel is the undercarriage of a KC-135R Stratotanker.
起落架由一根中心主轴构成，车轴和机轮都装在它上面
Landing gear comprises a central shaft to which an axle and wheels are attached.
他们开始加工主轴
They begin machining the shaft.
这台数控车床加工部件的外表面
This digital lathe machines the exterior surface of the part.
水和油的喷淋为因摩擦而发热的部件降温
Sprays of water and oil cool the part which heats up due to friction.
接下来对主轴进行穿孔
Next the shaft is pierced.
钻头将镗出主轴的内孔
The drill head will ream out the inside of the shaft.
钻头必须对准分毫不差
Alignment of the head must be perfect.
切削产生的切屑会被收集起来，卖给铸造厂回收利用
Turnings from the cutting are saved and these will be sold to foundries where they'll be recycled.
用于在起落架上钻孔的刀具必须极其锋利
The cutting tool used to pierce the holes in the landing gear has to be extremely sharp.
这台机床按需要将孔的两侧扩大
The hole is enlarged on its sides as required by this machine tool.
部件再次用水和油的混合液冷却
The part is again cooled with a mixture of water and oil.
切削完成后，用压缩空气清理孔洞，以便进行目视检查
Cutting is completed and the hole is now cleaned out with compressed air, so that they can proceed with a visual inspection.
接下来，3个部件由这台机床同时加工，因为将用于航空领域
Next, 3 pieces are rough cut at the same time by this machine, because they'll be used in aviation,
这些部件必须加工到完美无瑕
these pieces have to be machined to perfection.
主轴的加工现已接近完成
The machining of the shaft is now almost completed.
去毛刺机打磨加工过的表面
This deburring unit polishes the machined surfaces
用压缩空气工具和砂纸片进行抛光
with a compressed air tool and sandpaper discs.
现在必须检验部件的尺寸
And now they have to verify the dimensions of the parts.
这台数控机床有3个轴，能以极高的精度进行检验
This digitally controlled machine has 3 axes and does the verification with extreme precision.
另一台设备可加工尺寸更大的部件
Another unit allows for the machining of parts with greater dimensions.
这家工厂还翻新二手起落架
This facility also reconditions used landing gear,
比如这个来自波音707的起落架
such as this one from a Boeing 707.
他们用喷砂机除去油漆
They strip off the paint with a sandblaster to verify
以便精确检验部件的状态
the condition of the parts with great precision.
然而，仅凭目视检查是不够的
However, a visual inspection is not enough.
裂纹可通过磁粉聚集来检测
Cracks can be detected by magnetic particle concentration.
使部件磁化后，任何裂纹都会在紫外光下显现出来
They magnetize the part, and any cracks will become visible under ultraviolet light.
接下来是喷丸工艺，向金属表面喷射钢珠，以提高其抗疲劳性能
Now it's time for the shot metal procedure, where they spray steel balls onto the metal's surface to increase its resistance to fatigue.
在重新喷漆之前，先给部件镀层
Before repainting the part, they first plate it.
在镉液中浸泡10分钟
The part is immersed for 10 minutes in cadmium,
形成一层防腐蚀的保护镀层
which forms a protective coating that will resist corrosion.
然后在低浓度铬酸中快速浸洗
Then the part is quickly soaked in a weak concentration of chromic acid.
用气流搅动的水洗去铬酸
Water, agitated by air jets, cleans away the chromic acid,
再用水冲洗一次
and the part is rinsed with water once more.
随后在190摄氏度下烘烤23小时，以去除镀层过程中产生的氢
The part is now baked at 190 degrees over 23 hours to remove hydrogen induced during the plating process.
接着浸入零下129摄氏度的液氮中，使其尺寸收缩后再装配
Then the part is immersed in liquid nitrogen at minus 129 degrees centigrade before it's inserted, in order to reduce its size.
用液压千斤顶将套环压装上去
This collar is pushed on with a hydraulic jack.
套环受热后恢复原尺寸
Reheating the collar makes it return to its normal size.
现在将各部件和防漏接头装入活塞
Now the different components and the leak-proof joints are inserted into the piston.
减震器管装入活塞
The shock absorber tube goes into the piston.
这个部件在飞机着陆时吸收冲击应力
This part absorbs the shock stresses when an aircraft lands.
活塞现在滑入气缸，并确认减震器密封良好
The piston is now slid into the cylinder and verified that the shock absorber is leak-proof.
最后在烤箱中烘烤漆面，完成制造
Fabrication finishes with paint baked in an oven.
制造一套全新起落架需要6到8个月
It takes 6 to 8 months to make new landing gear,
而翻新一套二手的只需6到8周
and between 6 to 8 weeks to recondition a used one.
香水、眼影、粉底、口红
Perfume, eyeshadow, foundation, lipstick
这些都是由我们对美的追求所驱动的全球产业的产物
they're all products of a global industry driven by our desire for beauty.
有些产品含有50多种成分
But with over 50 ingredients going into some products,
其中大部分都会涂抹在我们的身体上
most of them destined to be slavered over our bodies,
因此这个行业必须以最高标准运作
this industry needs to work to the highest of standards.
化妆品自古以来就已存在
Cosmetics have been in existence since the dawn of time.
化妆品配方包含多种成分
There are many ingredients that make up a cosmetic formula.
该行业大量使用氧化铁，为产品调出多种色调
The industry relies heavily on iron oxides to color its products in a multitude of tones.
进入生产之前，每种原料都必须精确称量
Before moving into fabrication, each ingredient must be carefully and accurately weighed.
这些原料多为干性，比如粉末
These raw materials are often dry, such as powder,
但也可能是液体，甚至是油脂或蜡
but can be also liquid, even oil or wax.
每种成分都要先经过质量控制实验室的批准
Every ingredient will have first been approved by the quality control laboratory.
一个配方可能含有50多种成分
A single formula may contain over 50 ingredients.
另一种必不可少的成分是水
The other essential ingredient is water.
制作化妆品的水先经过反渗透系统净化
The water used in making cosmetics is first purified by an inverse osmosis system.
根据配方的复杂程度
Depending on the complexity of the recipe,
生产一种产品需要4到10小时
between 4 and 10 hours of work are needed to make up a product.
以泡泡浴配方为例
Take a bubble bath recipe.
配方的一部分在旁边的容器中配制，让某些成分更易溶解
A part of the recipe is prepared in an adjoining container to make certain ingredients more soluble.
不锈钢螺旋桨搅拌器将所有成分充分混合
A stainless steel screw propeller mixes all the ingredients thoroughly.
每一步，每种产品都要经过多项测试
At each step, each product will be subjected to many tests.
这里用颜色指示剂进行酸碱中和反应测试
Here, an acid-base neutralization reaction test is performed with a color indicator.
泡泡浴还需要上色
The bubble bath has to be colored.
加入香精和色素
A fragrance and color are added.
这样，最终成品会是淡紫色
In this case, the final product will be mauve.
在灌装之前
Before the filling process
质量控制实验室和微生物实验室会确保产品符合严格的质量标准
the quality control and microbiology laboratories make sure that the product meets strict quality standards.
现在进入下一道工序
Now it's onto the next step.
这台灌装机可同时灌装12瓶700毫升装
This filler can simultaneously fill up to 12 700
以每分钟50瓶的稳定速度灌装
milliliter bottles at a steady pace of 50 per minute.
灌装量由电子设备调节
The fill level is adjusted electronically.
接下来是封盖
Capping remains to be done.
这台封盖机自动定位并旋紧瓶盖
This capper positions and tightens the caps automatically.
聚氨酯辊施加精确的旋紧力度
Urethane rollers apply the precise tightening force.
瓶子现在经过感应封口机
The bottles now pass beneath the sealer via induction,
它会产生磁场
which generates a magnetic field,
加热瓶盖内的金属片
heating the metal piece placed in the cap.
温度足够高时，金属片就熔合在瓶口上
When hot enough, it welds itself onto the neck of the bottle.
这里生产的另一种产品是撕拉面膜
Another product made here is the peeling mask.
面膜被倒入这个漏斗中
The mask is poured into this funnel,
漏斗末端连接着灌装管
whose end is attached to the tube filler pipe.
产品依靠重力下落
The product descends by gravity.
灌装机每分钟将撕拉面膜灌入50支软管
The filler pours the peeling mask into 50 tubes each minute.
随后通过加热和压边封口，软管封口后即可包装
Then, with heat and crimping, the tube end is sealed and the tubes head for packaging.
这里还生产古龙水和香水
Other products made here: cologne and perfume water.
液体通过抽吸被吸入瓶内
The liquid is drawn into the bottle by suction.
瓶子被送至16个灌装喷头下方
Bottles are positioned beneath the 16 filling spouts,
喷头封住瓶口以形成真空，从而将产品吸入瓶内
which seal their opening to allow for the creation of a vacuum, which draws in the product.
现在插入喷雾泵
Now, atomizer pumps are inserted,
同时处理2个瓶子
Handling 2 bottles simultaneously.
这台机器封紧喷雾泵，将它固定在瓶口上
This machine seals the pump, securing it around the neck of the bottle.
白色套筒负责对准喷雾泵，灰色套筒则将其旋紧
The white sleeve aligns the pump, while the grey one tightens them.
接下来是喷头
Then there are the sprayers.
这台机器装上喷头
This machine applies the spray stoppers,
并用锤子把它们压到瓶泵上，瓶子至此完成
and with a hammer, presses them onto the pumps of the bottles, which are now finished.
最后一种产品：走珠止汗露
And one final product: roll-on deodorants.
这台机器每分钟灌装115瓶
This machine fills 115 bottles a minute,
一次处理8瓶
handling 8 bottles at a time.
灌装管将产品注入瓶中
A filling stem pours the product into the bottle,
然后以每分钟115个的速度放入走珠
and here they place the roller ball at 115 per minute.
随后走珠被轻轻压入凹槽，在其中自由转动
Then the ball is lightly pressed into the cavity, in which it turns freely.
这家工厂每年生产1200多种产品，销量达3200万件
This plant makes over 1,200 different products each year, and sells 32 million items.